<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-03-23T21:28:17-04:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">SciTECH</title><subtitle>Choate Rosemary Hall’s Science &amp; Technology Publication</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Apple September Event: The New iPhone, Apple Arcade and More</title><link href="/apple-iphone-event/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Apple September Event: The New iPhone, Apple Arcade and More" /><published>2019-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/apple-iphone-event</id><content type="html" xml:base="/apple-iphone-event/">&lt;p&gt;Just like every year since 2017, 2019’s edition of the Apple September Event was held at the Steve Jobs Theater at 1 Apple Park Way, Apple’s headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iphone-11-iphone-11-pro-and-iphone-11-pro-max&quot;&gt;iPhone 11, iPhone 11 Pro and iPhone 11 Pro Max&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important release from this year’s September Event has to be the newest members of the iPhone family: iPhone 11, iPhone 11 Pro and iPhone 11 Pro Max. Equipped with what Apple touts as the toughest glass ever on a smartphone and milled from a single sheet of glass, the new iPhone is made to resist damage from drops and scratches. The iPhone 11, the successor to the much loved iPhone XR, will come in six new colors: purple, white, yellow, green, black and Product Red, while the iPhone 11 Pro and iPhone 11 Pro Max will come in four colors: silver, gold, space gray and a brand new, sleek midnight green.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both phones are equipped with Apple’s new industry-leading processor, the 7nm A13 Bionic, which has not only 8.5 billion transistors, but also the fastest CPU and GPU ever in a smartphone. The CPU, GPU and neural engine of the A13 are all optimized for machine learning. Thanks to new machine learning accelerators, the A13 can conduct a trillion operations per second. Moreover, both devices have IP68 water resistance ratings, meaning that the iPhone 11 is water resistant up to 2m underwater for 30 minutes while the iPhone 11 Pro and 11 Pro Max are water resistant up to 4m underwater for 30 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the similarities between these two phones end here. The iPhone 11, like the XR before it has a 6.1 inch LCD display, with a 1792 by 828 pixel resolution at 326 ppi (pixels per inch). On the other hand, the iPhone 11 Pro and Pro Max have 5.8 and 6.5 inch Organic LED displays respectively, with 2436 by 1125 and 2688 by 1242 pixel resolutions, both at 458 ppi, which is the same as the iPhone X, iPhone XS and iPhone XS Max.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new iPhone 11 has two 12MP (Mega Pixel) cameras, one wide and one ultra wide while the Pros have an additional telephoto camera that allows them to have 10 times optical zoom compared to the 11’s 5. Lastly, all phones are speculated to have 4GB of RAM (Random Access Memory) and are offered with 64, 256 and 512GB of storage. Available from September 20th, the iPhone 11 starts at $699 while the iPhone 11 Pro starts at $999 and the iPhone 11 Pro Max starts at $1099.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;apple-arcade&quot;&gt;Apple Arcade&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the release of the new iPhone models was definitely the highlight of the event, the keynote did not begin with them, but rather with the introduction of Apple Arcade, the newest additional to Apple’s burgeoning services branch. Available exclusively on the App Store, the game subscription service for mobiles, desktops and TVs gives unlimited access to over a hundred new games created by Apple in cooperation with various other innovative game developers. Apple Arcade will be available starting September 19th with a family subscription fee of $4.99 a month, which includes 1 month free trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;apple-tv&quot;&gt;Apple TV+&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple TV+ is Apple’s new subscription based streaming service available for all Apple devices. Available from November 1st in over 100 countries, a family subscription fee will be $4.99 a month. Even better, if you buy an iPhone, iPad, Mac or Apple TV, one year of Apple TV+ will be included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ipados-and-102-ipad&quot;&gt;iPadOS and 10.2” iPad&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newest addition to the iPad is iPadOS, an operating system derived from iOS and designed specifically for the iPad. It will be available to all Choate students free of charge once permission is given from the IT Department. Apple claims the new iPadOS “adds new capabilities and intuitive features that are specific to the large display and versatility of iPad.” Among them include new simplified multitasking and app sliding functions, a new smaller screen keyboard that can be accessed by pinching the preexisting keyboard, along with the ability to crop videos and SD card and thumb drive support among other functions. In addition, Apple released the 7th generation budget iPad, now equipped with a new 10.2” retina display and powered by Apple’s A10 Fusion chip (the same chip that powered the iPhone 7 and 7 Plus, which were introduced back in 2016). Moreover, the smart connector and Apple Pencil support has finally arrived to the new iPad, which will be priced at $329, available September 30th. Last but certainly not least, the enclosure of the new 10.2” iPad is made from 100% recycled aluminum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;apple-watch--series-5&quot;&gt;Apple Watch  Series 5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple Watch has been the staple of practical smartwatches ever since its release back in April of 2015. From a design standpoint, Apple Watch Series 5 is virtually identical to its predecessor, the Series 4. However, the new watch has a retina always-on display, which dims instead of shutting off when it senses you are not looking at it. Despite having the screen on at all times, the new Apple Watch still maintains 18 hours battery life, the same as the previous Apple Watch thanks to energy optimization. Additionally, the new Apple Watch has a built in compass, which can be used in both the Compass app and Maps. Every cellular equipped Apple Watch Series 5 is equipped with international emergency calling, allowing you to call over 150 different emergency services from around the world. For the first time, the App Store will come to the Apple Watch via WatchOS 6, allowing developers to create Apple Watch orientated applications. Moreover, new useful apps for the Watch have been added such as the Noise app, which measures the decibel count of your surrounding area and alerts you if something is too loud, and the Cycle Tracking App which makes it easier to log information, keep track of your menstrual cycle and receive alerts when your period is likely to begin. Lastly, in addition to several new watch faces being announced, Apple revealed the Apple Watch Studio, a place where you can mix and match an Apple Watch to see what it is like before buying it. Apple proudly claims that there are nearly 1000 different ways to select your Apple Watch and are offering dozens of colors and textures of watch bands in addition to four different cases: ceramic, aluminium, stainless steel or titanium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the contents of this year’s September Event certainly were not the most unexpected, it did include some welcomed additions to the Apple ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;September Event 2019 - Apple [Motion picture]. (2019). USA: Apple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;de Looper, C. (2019, June 3). The App Store will come to the Apple Watch with
     WatchOS 6. Retrieved September 29, 2019, from Digital Trends website:
     https://www.digitaltrends.com/apple/watchos-6-news/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;de Looper, C. (2019, September 10). Apple Watch Series 5: All you need to know
     about Apple’s new smartwatch. Retrieved September 29, 2019, from Digital
     Trends website: https://www.digitaltrends.com/wearables/
     apple-watch-series-5-news/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lopez, R. (2019, September 11). MEET THE IPHONE 11 PRO, IPHONE 11 PRO MAX.
     SPECS, PRICES HERE. Retrieved September 29, 2019, from Revu website:
     https://www.revu.com.ph/2019/09/iphone-11-pro-vs-11-pro-max-specs-prices/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lopez, R. (2019, September 15). IPHONE 11 SERIES GETS HIGHEST BENCHMARK SCORES IN ANTUTU, GEEKBENCH. Retrieved September 29, 2019, from Revu website:
     https://www.revu.com.ph/2019/09/iphone-11-pro-max-top-benchmark-scores/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lanaria, V. (2019, September 16). iPhone 11, iPhone 11 Pro Benchmark: Early
     Tests Reveal All Models Have 4 GB RAM. Retrieved September 29, 2019, from
     Tech Times website: https://www.techtimes.com/articles/245376/20190916/
     Iphone-11-iphone-11-pro-benchmark-early-tests-reveal-all-models-have-4-gb-ram.htm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smartphone Processors Ranking. (2019, September 27). Retrieved September 29,
     2019, from Techrankup website: https://www.techrankup.com/articles/
     smartphone-processors-ranking/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simonite, T. (2017, September 13). Apple’s ‘Neural Engine’ Infuses the iPhone
     With AI Smarts. Retrieved September 29, 2019, from Wired website:
     https://www.wired.com/story/
     apples-neural-engine-infuses-the-iphone-with-ai-smarts/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mansurov, N. (2019, August 24). Understanding Aperture in Photography. Retrieved
     September 30, 2019, from Photographylife website:
     https://photographylife.com/what-is-aperture-in-photography&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goode, L. (2019, September 17). Review: Apple iPhone 11 Pro. Retrieved September
     30, 2019, from Wired website: https://www.wired.com/review/
     apple-iphone-11-pro/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haslam, O. (2019, September 12). iPhone 11 Pro appears in Geekbench and has 4GB
     of RAM. Or does it? Retrieved September 30, 2019, from iMore website:
     https://www.imore.com/iphone-11-pro-appears-geekbench-and-has-4gb-ram-or-does-it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La, L. (2019, September 28). iPhone 11, 11 Pro and 11 Pro Max specs vs. iPhone
     XR, XS and XS Max: What’s new and different. Retrieved September 30, 2019,
     from CNET website: https://www.cnet.com/news/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Performance Ranking of V7. (2019, August). Retrieved September 30, 2019, from
     AnTuTu Benchmark website: https://browser.geekbench.com/v5/compute/
     search?utf8=✓&amp;amp;q=iphone&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geekbench 4 CPU Search. (n.d.). Retrieved September 30, 2019, from Geekbench
     Browser website: https://browser.geekbench.com/v4/cpu/
     search?utf8=✓&amp;amp;q=iphone+11&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Performance Ranking of V7 - Android. (2019, August). Retrieved September 30,
     2019, from AnTuTu Benchmark website: https://www.antutu.com/en/ranking/
     rank1.htm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple. Retrieved September 30, 2019, from Apple website:
     https://www.apple.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>ryan_kim_23</name></author><summary type="html">Just like every year since 2017, 2019’s edition of the Apple September Event was held at the Steve Jobs Theater at 1 Apple Park Way, Apple’s headquarters.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/apple-september-2019.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dr. Selena Gell: From Scientific Research to Teaching</title><link href="/gell-from-science-research-to-testing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dr. Selena Gell: From Scientific Research to Teaching" /><published>2019-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/gell-from-science-research-to-testing</id><content type="html" xml:base="/gell-from-science-research-to-testing/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;During her time at Choate, Dr. Gell has taught Honors Biology and Molecular and Cell Biology. Dr. Gell has an extremely strong research background with five years of work as a PhD student and five more as a postdoctoral researcher. This knowledge and experience allows her to teach a variety of classes and successfully train Choate students in true scientific research while leading the biology section of Choate’s Scientific Research Program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Gell was captivated by the scientific world from a young age. As a child, Dr. Gell was surrounded by family friends who were scientists and lead lives full of interesting people, ceaseless learning, and careers that improved the world through scientific advancement. On top of this, Dr. Gell possessed an innate interest in the natural world, often catching frogs and insects while spending most of her time outdoors. By the time she entered high school, she knew she wanted to become a scientist and eagerly took all of the science classes that were available to her. Beyond taking the normal sciences in high school, Dr. Gell also participated in an internship at an animal forensic laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For college, Dr. Gell attended Brandeis University where she considered majoring in either chemistry or biology. Eventually, Dr. Gell’s interest in the work of some of her biology professors led her to choose biology and work in the Fulton Lab at Brandeis. While working in the lab, Dr. Gell studied a form of programmed cell death known as apoptosis, which has applications in developmental processes and cancer. This initial exposure to scientific research strengthened Dr. Gell’s goal to pursue a PhD in science. However, Dr. Gell knew that she wanted to take a break from her traditional education for a couple of years in order to participate in something new that benefited the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After graduation, Dr. Gell worked with Teach for America for two years while teaching chemistry, biology, and physical science at a low-income high school in Phoenix, Arizona. Although this wasn’t the experience that initially revealed a passion for teaching within Dr. Gell, it most definitely helped shape the idea of incorporating more teaching in her future career. To combine her interests in both teaching and research, Dr. Gell decided to pursue a PhD at Brown with the goal of working at a small liberal arts college with a lab of her own in the future. For her PhD in molecular and cell biology, Dr. Gell studied selfish genetic elements using fruit flies in the Rob Reenan lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once finished with her formal education, Dr. Gell became a post-doctoral research fellow at Harvard Medical school. During her time at Harvard, Dr. Gell studied protein complexes involved in gene regulation, using the same yeast found in beer and bread. After five years of dedicated research work at Harvard Medical School, Dr. Gell stumbled across a job opportunity at Choate. Dr. Gell felt that the career opportunity offered by Choate would allow her to return to the teaching aspect she loved about science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One life lesson that Dr. Gell learned from her experience as a scientific researcher is persistence: “In science, most of the things you do fail. You try to experiment, it doesn’t work the first five times you do it, it doesn’t work the first ten times you do it. Every time you do it slightly differently, changing a variable until suddenly, one day, you actually get a result.” She also notes the importance of time management as a key component to a successful life and career, “being in science taught me a lot about balance in my life and having to make time for things that are important to me outside of work. Being a researcher is the kind of job that can expand to fill all available time and I had to learn how to set aside time for me so that I came back to my work exited, refreshed, and ready to take on challenges.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things Dr. Gell set aside time for apart from her work life, was competitive rugby. In fact, Dr. Gell played competitive rugby for twelve years after starting in college at Brandeis. She also played for The Lady Blues while living in Arizona and Providence women’s rugby while at Brown, before retiring in 2012. Ultimately, competitive rugby provided Dr. Gell with an extremely useful outlet to refresh her mind from the demanding workload of college and laboratory research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With such an impressive background in both the academic and the athletic world, Dr. Gell serves as a perfect example of why being a Choate student is such an invaluable opportunity and experience. Faculty members like Dr. Gell allows us to not only receive an amazing education, but also learn important life lessons from their experiences. Together, this knowledge and wisdom are truly the reasons why so many Choate alumni have regarded their time here as priceless.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>max_connor_21</name></author><summary type="html">During her time at Choate, Dr. Gell has taught Honors Biology and Molecular and Cell Biology. Dr. Gell has an extremely strong research background with five years of work as a PhD student and five more as a postdoctoral researcher. This knowledge and experience allows her to teach a variety of classes and successfully train Choate students in true scientific research while leading the biology section of Choate’s Scientific Research Program.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/superelastic-cell-graphic.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">In Space, No One Can Hear You Scream</title><link href="/space-screaming-hearing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In Space, No One Can Hear You Scream" /><published>2019-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/space-screaming-hearing</id><content type="html" xml:base="/space-screaming-hearing/">&lt;p&gt;Nearly four years after the monumental observation of gravitational waves, scientists have detected tones in the “ringing” of a black hole for the first time, corroborating yet another one of Einstein’s theoretical predictions. According to Einstein’s theory of general relativity, a black hole formed from the collision of two other black holes produces “ringing” gravitational waves. However, what is special about the ringing of these gravitational waves is that they encode specific information about the nature of the black hole, namely their mass, spin, and electric charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On September 14, 2015, scientists first detected gravitational waves using LIGO, the Laser Interferometer Gravitational-wave Observatory. Gravitational waves are waves that transport energy in the form of gravitational radiation and propagate through a gravitational field, creating a ripple-like effect in space in the process. In order to study gravitational waves, scientists have translated the signals into sound waves, which crescendo over time. When black holes merge, the gravitational waves translate into a “chirping” sound. The chirp is loudest at the moment when the black holes fuse. The infant black hole that is created from the collision of the two parent black holes also produces gravitational waves that “ring;” however, physicists previously assumed that the noise created by the infant would be too faint to interpret amid the loud noise from the initial collision of the parents. Therefore, traces of this ringing have to be studied sometime after the peak, when the signal becomes too faint to be of much significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team that published the findings, led by Maximiliano Isi of MIT’s Kavli Institute for Astrophysics and Space Research, found a way to extract a black hole’s reverberation from instants after the signal’s peak. In previous work led by Isi’s co-author, Matthew Giesler of Caltech, the same team showed that the signal, particularly the portion immediately after the peak, contained “overtones,” which are loud, short-lived tones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We detect an overall gravitational wave signal that’s made up of different frequencies, which fade away at different rates, like the different pitches that make up a sound,” Isi said for the MIT news. “Each frequency or tone corresponds to a vibrational frequency of the new black hole.”When the team took the overtones into account, they were able to identify a ringing pattern specific to a newly-formed black hole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This was a very surprising result. The conventional wisdom was that by the time the remnant black hole had settled down so that any tones could be detected, the overtones would have decayed away almost completely,” noted Saul Teukolsky, the Robinson Professor of Theoretical Astrophysics at Caltech and adviser to Giesler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using these ringing patterns, physicists were able to use the equations Einstein outlined in his theory of general relativity to calculate the mass and spin of the black hole. These measurements concurred with previous measurements. If they had not matched, then the ringing patterns would have encoded more information than the mass, spin, and electrical charge of the black hole. However, the extra information would have violated Einstein’s No-Hair Theorem, stating that the only characteristics needed to define a black hole are mass, spin, and electrical charge, without any “excess hairs.” The alignment of these measurements with Einstein’s theory is significant as it paves the way for more advanced work in ringing patterns in the future with better equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As LIGO improves its resolution techniques and more sensitive instruments are developed, scientists will be able to use the ideas put forth by Giesler and the Isi team to “hear” the ringing of other newborn black holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the future, we’ll have better detectors on Earth and in space, and we will be able to see not just two, but tens of modes, and pin down their properties precisely,” Isi remarked. “If these are not black holes as Einstein predicts, if they are more exotic objects like wormholes or boson stars, they may not ring in the same way, and we’ll have a chance of seeing them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, the future of ringing patterns is abuzz with potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blair, D., Dr. (2018, March 12). Why you can hear gravitational waves when things collide in the universe. Retrieved October 23, 2019, from The Conversation website: https://theconversation.com/explainer-why-you-can-hear-gravitational-waves-when-things-collide-in-the-universe-92356&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chu, J. (2019, September 12). Scientists detect tones in the ringing of a newborn black hole for the first time. Retrieved October 13, 2019, from MIT News website: http://news.mit.edu/2019/ringing-new-black-hole-first-0912&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clavin, W. (n.d.). First ‘overtones’ heard in the ringing of a black hole. Retrieved October 13, 2019, from Phys.org website: https://phys.org/news/2019-09-overtones-heard-black-hole.html&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspiral Gravitational Waves. (n.d.). Retrieved October 23, 2019, from LIGO Scientific Collaboration website: https://www.ligo.org/science/GW-Inspiral.php&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathur, S. (n.d.). The no-hair theorem [Lecture transcript]. Retrieved October 13, 2019, from Ohio State University Department of Physics website: https://www.asc.ohio-state.edu/mathur.16/gian/bhdrivershortnh.pdf&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>sophie_vulpe_22</name></author><summary type="html">Nearly four years after the monumental observation of gravitational waves, scientists have detected tones in the “ringing” of a black hole for the first time, corroborating yet another one of Einstein’s theoretical predictions. According to Einstein’s theory of general relativity, a black hole formed from the collision of two other black holes produces “ringing” gravitational waves. However, what is special about the ringing of these gravitational waves is that they encode specific information about the nature of the black hole, namely their mass, spin, and electric charge.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/black-hole-graphic.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Your Package Has Been Delivered – By a Drone</title><link href="/package-drone-delivered/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your Package Has Been Delivered – By a Drone" /><published>2019-12-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/package-drone-delivered</id><content type="html" xml:base="/package-drone-delivered/">&lt;p&gt;As the demand for faster deliveries rises, many retail corporations in the US are working to implement new and innovative methods to transport their products to their customers. Adding automation and artificial intelligence are ways a company can not only manufacture and deliver the items faster but also reduce the cost of manual labor. Thus, many major retailers are moving towards implementing drone delivery services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest e-commerce retailer in the world, Amazon, is about to implement all-electric autonomous drones into their delivery process. Announced at their inaugural re:Mars Conference in 2019, an event discussing the latest innovations in robotics and machine learning, Amazon’s recent delivery drones can fly up to fifteen miles and deliver packages to customers in less than thirty minutes. The drones use various sensors and algorithms to detect objects impeding their path and the surrounding environment. “We know customers will only feel comfortable receiving drone deliveries if they know the system is incredibly safe,” said Jeff Wilke, the CEO of Amazon’s worldwide consumer division. “So, we’re building a drone that isn’t just safe, but independently safe, using the latest artificial intelligence technologies.” Amazon’s delivery drones also have a positive impact on the environment. Lowering carbon emission and the use of fossils, drones run totally on electric power and is a sustainable alternative to the conventional trucks used to carry their products. By 2030, Amazon plans to make half of all their deliveries carbon-free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to Amazon, Walgreens and FedEx are also launching their own automated drone programs. Executing “final-mile deliveries, improving access to health care products, and creating possible new growth for local businesses” are the company’s objectives in this project. Partnering with Wing Aviation, a subsidiary of Google, Walgreens would possibly be the first US retailer to provide on-demand commercial drone delivery. By using drones, the company said it will make over-the-counter medicines, food, and other products available to nearby residents within minutes after their order. Walgreens already has 9,700 stores nationwide, and, therefore, would be able to capitalize on the drone delivery services. Walgreens is currently testing its drone delivery service in Christiansburg, VA because of Wing’s connections with the Virginia Tech Mid-Atlantic Aviation Partnership, a test site for unmanned aircraft. Final-mile delivery is the biggest component of the overall cost for companies and utilizing drones instead of people will lower their expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the advantages drones give to companies, there are still some issues that need addressing. The biggest concern the public have involves the invasion of privacy. Many companies install cameras into their drones to make sure the product is successfully delivered and to avoid trees and other obstacles in the way. However, the camera may accidentally take a video of people and properties who aren’t associated with the transaction. Therefore, drone regulations needs to be updated in the future if they will be used as a staple mode of transporting goods for retail companies. However, despite these issues, drone delivery services are the next step in engineering and transportation. The efficiency and convenience of drone delivery will create a huge impact on people’s lives in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hitti, Natashah. “Amazon to Deliver Purchases by Drone ‘within Months.’” Dezeen, Dezeen, 9 June 2019, www.dezeen.com/2019/06/06/amazon-prime-air-drone-news/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regoli, Natalie. “18 Delivery Drones Pros and Cons.” Vittana.org, vittana.org/18-delivery-drones-pros-and-cons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stinson, Jim. “Walgreens, FedEx Express Partner With Google Parent on Drones.” Transport Topics, 25 Sept. 2019, www.ttnews.com/articles/walgreens-fedex-express-partner-google-parent-drones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tyko, Kelly. “Amazon Prime Air Delivery Drone to Start Dropping Packages ‘within Months,’ Officials Say.” USA Today, Gannett Satellite Information Network, 7 June 2019, www.usatoday.com/story/money/2019/06/05/amazon-drone-delivery-shopping-giant-unveils-new-prime-air-drone/1358260001/.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>praj_chirathivat_22</name></author><summary type="html">As the demand for faster deliveries rises, many retail corporations in the US are working to implement new and innovative methods to transport their products to their customers. Adding automation and artificial intelligence are ways a company can not only manufacture and deliver the items faster but also reduce the cost of manual labor. Thus, many major retailers are moving towards implementing drone delivery services.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/delivery-drone.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hydrogels: The Miracle Cure for Heart Attacks</title><link href="/hydrogels-heart-attack/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hydrogels: The Miracle Cure for Heart Attacks" /><published>2019-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/hydrogels-heart-attack</id><content type="html" xml:base="/hydrogels-heart-attack/">&lt;p&gt;Every 40 seconds, someone in the US experiences a heart attack, amounting to an average of 790,000 cases annually. A heart attack occurs when there is reduced blood flow to a section of the heart, resulting in damaged tissue or dead cells. One out of every five heart attacks is show no other symptoms, but damage is still done to the muscle. Following a heart attack, the heart muscles are weakened, resulting in thinner chamber walls and a frail heart. With cardiovascular disease on the rise—nearly half of adults in the U.S. are afflicted—researchers are coming up with a new treatment plan: using hydrogels to repair the heart following a heart attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no current cure to repair the damage done after a heart attack as scar tissue forms around the heart and diminishes the efficacy of the muscles, leading to heart failure. Now, a company called Ventrix, based at the University of California, San Diego, has successfully conducted the first successful human trial of using an injectable hydrogel to repair the damage, stimulate muscle regeneration, and restore cardiac function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VentriGel, the hydrogel compound injected into the heart, works as a scaffold that facilitates a curative environment for healthy cells to repopulate. The hydrogel substance is made from cardiac connective tissue from pigs. It is then stripped of the heart muscle cells the human body would reject and run through an extensive cleansing process. Afterward, it is freeze-dried and converted to a powder form to be liquified into an injectable, semi-solid and porous fluid for the minimally invasive procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main goal of the Phase 1 trial was to evaluate the safety and feasibility of VentriGel in 7 patients who suffered a heart attack within the past year and 8 who suffered a heart attack three or more years ago. Following the injection into the damaged regions of the heart and patient tracking for six months after the treatment, the Ventrix team reported that the hydrogel was effective and showed no adverse effects. In fact, VentriGel nearly restored the damaged heart chamber walls to their original condition before the heart attack. The trial completed its goal to measure the effects of the hydrogel and whether it improves cardiac function of the patients and helps them walk longer distances enabled by improved heart health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the success of Phase 1, Ventrix is preparing for the Phase 2 clinical trial consisting of a larger, randomized trial. While this FDA-approved Phase 1 clinical trial is monumental progress, there is still much work to be done in this field of research. In the coming years, hydrogel treatment may be able to terminate deaths due to heart failure following a heart attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hydrogel to repair heart proves safe to inject in humans. (2019, September 12). Retrieved from https://physicsworld.com/a/hydrogel-to-repair-heart-proves-safe-to-inject-in-humans/#targetText=Hydrogel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FDA phase 1 trial shows hydrogel to repair heart is safe to inject in humans – a first. (2019, September 11). Retrieved from https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2019/09/190911142821.htm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heart Attack Facts &amp;amp; Statistics. (2017, August 18). Retrieved from https://www.cdc.gov/heartdisease/heart_attack.htm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sandoiu, A. (2019, February 2). Cardiovascular deaths on the rise in the US. Retrieved from https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/324351.php#targetText.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>henrik_torres_22</name></author><summary type="html">Every 40 seconds, someone in the US experiences a heart attack, amounting to an average of 790,000 cases annually. A heart attack occurs when there is reduced blood flow to a section of the heart, resulting in damaged tissue or dead cells. One out of every five heart attacks is show no other symptoms, but damage is still done to the muscle. Following a heart attack, the heart muscles are weakened, resulting in thinner chamber walls and a frail heart. With cardiovascular disease on the rise—nearly half of adults in the U.S. are afflicted—researchers are coming up with a new treatment plan: using hydrogels to repair the heart following a heart attack.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Q&amp;amp;A with Mr. John Ford: Being a Well-rounded Scientist</title><link href="/q-a-john-ford-well-rounded/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Q&amp;A with Mr. John Ford: Being a Well-rounded Scientist" /><published>2019-12-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/q-a-john-ford-well-rounded</id><content type="html" xml:base="/q-a-john-ford-well-rounded/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This year at Convocation, Mr. John Ford, a long-time Choate science teacher, received a faculty chair for his incredible dedication and passion for teaching. Recently, I had a chance to sit down with Mr. Ford to talk about his background in STEM and teaching, as well as some fun facts and advice for students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-is-your-background-in-stem&quot;&gt;Q: What is your background in STEM?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: I was a biology major in college, and I also did some graduate work in similar fields for my master’s degree. In my 45 years of teaching or so, I’ve taught all levels of biology as well as first-year physics and first-year chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-made-you-decide-to-pursue-a-career-in-stem&quot;&gt;Q: What made you decide to pursue a career in STEM?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: When I was in high school, I found that both my strength and interest was more in STEM areas — particularly, my interest was in biology. In high school, I never really took to the more verbal courses, English and history. I worked hard in them, but they just didn’t come as easily to me as STEM classes. And when I went off to college, I was pretty certain that I was going to major in biology — and I did. Sometimes people change their minds, but I didn’t. I did find some areas of biology that I didn’t know I would be interested in until I was exposed to them in college, which was good. I got to do a little bit of research with a couple of professors, and so I continued to pursue it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-are-your-views-on-stem-education-at-choate-and-beyond&quot;&gt;Q: What are your views on STEM education at Choate and beyond?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: I worry a little bit about over-specialization. I think that sometimes high school students are too quick to specialize in an area and therefore dispense with other areas that they don’t realize they might have an interest. So I’m more of a fan of a general education, or what we consider a liberal arts education. I think that it’s really important, no matter what you’re doing, to be reasonably experienced in reading, writing, and scientific thinking, as well as quantitative skills. I don’t think any high school student should be avoiding any of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-are-some-important-things-you-think-choates-future-scientists-should-know&quot;&gt;Q: What are some important things you think Choate’s future scientists should know?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: I think that what they should be careful of is getting too far down the road with something supposedly advanced in study without having a really good coverage of fundamentals. I worry sometimes when I see what students are doing in SRP in that they are looking at some pretty intricate and detailed studies related to their summer work in the lab, and that’s at the expense of covering the fundamentals. So what I think Choate science students should know is that it’s okay to take your time. Make sure that you don’t rush ahead into detailed, advanced work without covering core concepts first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;q-what-are-your-proudest-stem-or-education-accomplishments&quot;&gt;Q: What are your proudest STEM or education accomplishments?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A: In my earlier days, my primary area of interest was in marine biology, and I think I did quite a few things to establish the study of marine science here at Choate. It’s been a long time since I’ve taught it here, but I laid a lot of groundwork for that. I did some pretty good and fun research myself, especially in coastal marine ecosystems and coral reef ecosystems.
Q: What is your favorite book and/or character?
A: I guess still my favorite book is The Catcher in the Rye and my favorite character is Holden Caulfield. It’s hard to pick one favorite, but I feel like Holden Caulfield has been with me for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>claire_yuan_22</name></author><summary type="html">This year at Convocation, Mr. John Ford, a long-time Choate science teacher, received a faculty chair for his incredible dedication and passion for teaching. Recently, I had a chance to sit down with Mr. Ford to talk about his background in STEM and teaching, as well as some fun facts and advice for students.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Warmer Climate, Denser Ice</title><link href="/warmer-climate-denser-ice/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Warmer Climate, Denser Ice" /><published>2019-12-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/warmer-climate-denser-ice</id><content type="html" xml:base="/warmer-climate-denser-ice/">&lt;p&gt;With youth-led strikes all over the world demanding change and the UN 25th International Climate Conference coming up in Chile, climate change is becoming an increasingly relevant issue today. New studies come out every year on the topic; one bleak discovery after another appearing on various news outlets. The newest information: the Greenland ice sheet is getting denser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a heat wave struck Greenland this year, over half of the Greenlandic ice sheet—the second largest after the Antarctic ice sheet—started melting at an unprecedented pace for the first time since 2012. A study published by Nature stated that along with the sudden increase in melting ice, amplified by the warming climate, the ice sheet is becoming denser as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people believe Greenland is a thick wall of impenetrable ice. In reality, about 80 percent of the ice is fresh snow layered on top of thicker, older snow, called firn, which in turn is compressed into glacial ice over time. As firn contains many air pockets, liquid water melting from the surface normally gets trapped inside. Through a complex “plumbing” system, firn then absorbs the water like a sponge. Data from a radio-echo sound (a kind of ultrasound machine for ice) showed in 2014 that some ice is stored within the crevices of the system until the arrival of winter, when they are either released back into the system or refrozen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summer of 2012, a group of researchers noticed that the Greenlandic ice was behaving differently. They found fully compact, solid slabs of ice right beneath the freshly fallen snow. The lack of air pockets prevented runoff water from entering the ice sheet; instead, they transferred straight into the ocean. Every summer of increased melting leads to a thicker and harder slab of ice spreading inland to higher and colder grounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to global warming, the ice is melting at an unprecedented pace. Now, glaciers are losing one billion tons of ice per day, and the runoff has expanded by 26 percent. Researchers estimate that ice slab proliferation has the potential to add three inches to sea levels by 2100, a third of all the current contributions to sea level rise. In addition, glaciologists pointed out that the slabs of ice are not nearly as reflective as firn. The ice absorbs more solar radiation than firn and warms up, resulting in the formation of even more slabs, a vicious cycle that sets off a slew of environmental issues. Some runoff might not even flow into the ocean. They might end up at the very bottom of the sheet, assisting as a slippery slide and lubricating the area where ice comes in contact, leading to the sheet flowing towards the ocean with more ease than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest contribution of this study, however, is a deeper understanding of Greenlandic ice patterns. With this information, scientists are now able to predict with higher accuracy the predictions of future sea level rise in order to assist threatened coastal communities. Scientists also gained an increased awareness that the more carbon the world is emitting into the atmosphere, the more likely the Earth’s northern ice sheet would be unpredictably transformed in an insidious manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cassella, C. (n.d.). The Greenland Ice Sheet Has Been Hiding a Surprising Amount of Liquid Water. Retrieved September 29, 2019, from ScienceAlert website: https://www.sciencealert.com/below-greenland-ice-sheet-surprising-amount-liquid-water-climate-models&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chain reaction of fast-draining lakes poses new risk for Greenland ice sheet. (2018, March 14). Retrieved September 29, 2019, from University of Cambridge website: https://www.cam.ac.uk/research/news/chain-reaction-of-fast-draining-lakes-poses-new-risk-for-greenland-ice-sheet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kendrick, A. K., Schroeder, D. M., Chu, W., Young, T. J., Christoffersen, P., Todd, J., … Lok, L. B. (2018). Surface Meltwater Impounded by Seasonal Englacial Storage in West Greenland. Geophysical Research Letters, 45(19), 10,474-10,481. https://doi.org/10.1029/2018GL079787&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MacFerrin, M., Machguth, H., As, D. van, Charalampidis, C., Stevens, C. M., Heilig, A., … Abdalati, W. (2019). Rapid expansion of Greenland’s low-permeability ice slabs. Nature, 573(7774), 403–407. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-019-1550-3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machguth, H., MacFerrin, M., van As, D., Box, J. E., Charalampidis, C., Colgan, W., … van de Wal, R. S. W. (2016). Greenland meltwater storage in firn limited by near-surface ice formation. Nature Climate Change, 6(4), 390–393. https://doi.org/10.1038/nclimate2899&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nield, D. (n.d.). A Runaway Chain Reaction Under The Greenland Ice Sheet Is Threatening Its Collapse. Retrieved September 29, 2019, from ScienceAlert website: https://www.sciencealert.com/chain-reaction-draining-lakes-threatening-greenland-ice-sheet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists find missing piece in glacier melt predictions. (n.d.). Retrieved September 29, 2019, from ScienceDaily website: https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2018/10/181015100508.htm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something strange is happening to Greenland’s ice sheet. (2019, September 18). Retrieved September 29, 2019, from Environment website: https://www.nationalgeographic.com/environment/2019/09/greenland-ice-getting-denser-thats-bad/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>claire_fu_22</name></author><summary type="html">With youth-led strikes all over the world demanding change and the UN 25th International Climate Conference coming up in Chile, climate change is becoming an increasingly relevant issue today. New studies come out every year on the topic; one bleak discovery after another appearing on various news outlets. The newest information: the Greenland ice sheet is getting denser.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/ice-core-blue.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Discovery of Superelastic Properties in Mammalian Epithelial Cells</title><link href="/superelastic-mammalian-epithelial-cells/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discovery of Superelastic Properties in Mammalian Epithelial Cells" /><published>2019-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/superelastic-mammalian-epithelial-cells</id><content type="html" xml:base="/superelastic-mammalian-epithelial-cells/">&lt;p&gt;In October 2018, Nature published a study titled “Active superelasticity in three-dimensional epithelia of controlled shape”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; which provided evidence for the appearance of cell superelasticity in mammalian epithelial cells upon undergoing extreme tension. Superelasticity, a property usually found in metallic alloys, is characterized by a cell’s ability to completely reverse large-scale deformations and elongate itself without increased force&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. During this state, cells develop liquid-like properties and no longer become resistant to tension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this study, mammalian epithelial cells were chosen because of their known ability to resist tension as well as their ability to pump water from their upper side to their lower side&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The water would then form a dome under the cells which would create tension and cause the cells to elongate (Figure 1a). During this process, some of the cells became superelastic, stretching to a wider cell surface than the elastic cells (Figure 1b). Adhesion junctions, the connecting area between cells, are the weakest points of pressure and eventually rupture from the increasing force. As a result, the water is able to escape from the dome which releases the tension from the cells (Figure 1c). Since none of the cells were in a state of plasticity, where irreversible damage can be done to the cellular shape3, all the cells return to their original, compacted position with superelastic cells appearing the same as other cells (Figure 1d).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, scientists believed cells under identical tension would have the same degree of shape deformation, but this experiment also shows that different cells have different thresholds for superelasticity. As shown in Figure 1, not all of the epithelial cells become superelastic at the same time, which researchers theorized was a result of the varied cellular mechanical properties (such as sensitivity to tension) of each cell&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Additionally, only under specific conditions can a cell enter a state of superelasticity. Cells that are placed under rapidly increasing pressure, even for a short duration, usually rupture while cells with slowly increasing pressure are able to maintain the dome structure for over hours&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this study has provided insight into a topic on which there was very limited understanding, there are still many questions left regarding cellular superelasticity. For one, there is still no definite reason as to why this occurs. Latorre et al. examined the connection between a cell’s cortex thickness and its superelastic threshold but there wasn’t substantial evidence supporting this hypothesis. The cell cortex is composed mainly of actin filaments, cytoskeletal filaments that maintain cellular structure and shape by relaying forces both within and between cells&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. They hoped to show that cellular stretching resulted in the breaking apart of these filaments which would lead to a superelastic state, but the results didn’t show a direct correlation&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. But, they were able to show the involvement of intermediate filaments, filaments that only provide mechanical strength to cells and are not involved in cellular movement1. When intermediate filaments in superelastic cells underwent laser ablation (essentially removing them), cell surface increased, which showed that they had resisted tension and were load-bearing (a theory that was suggested due to their unusually stiff structure in super-stretched cells)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. From this, they theorized that the weakness of the cortex induces support from the intermediate filaments and helps the cell elongate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery of cellular elasticity has important implications on researching other cellular processes, such as the spreading and compaction of super-stretched embryonic tissue&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and can also lead to developments in cellular mechanics and engineering. By further examining cellular properties, mechanics, and processes like morphogenesis, we may reach a better understanding of what cellular elasticity is and how it impacts our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Latorre, E., Kale, S., Casares, L., Gómez-González, M., Uroz, M., Valon, L., . . . Trepat, X. (2018, 10). Active superelasticity in three-dimensional epithelia of controlled shape. Nature, 563(7730), 203-208. doi:10.1038/s41586-018-0671-4 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Théry, M., &amp;amp; Asnacios, A. (2018, 10). Cellular stretch reveals superelastic powers. Nature, 563(7730), 192-194. doi:10.1038/d41586-018-07172-9 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yirka, B. (2018, 11). Researchers find that cells can at times have superelastic properties. Retrieved from Phys.org website: https://phys.org/news/2018-11-cells-superelastic-properties.html &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Cooper GM. The Cell: A Molecular Approach. 2nd edition. Sunderland (MA): Sinauer Associates; 2000. Intermediate Filaments. Available from: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK9834/ &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>amanda_li_21</name></author><summary type="html">In October 2018, Nature published a study titled “Active superelasticity in three-dimensional epithelia of controlled shape”1 which provided evidence for the appearance of cell superelasticity in mammalian epithelial cells upon undergoing extreme tension. Superelasticity, a property usually found in metallic alloys, is characterized by a cell’s ability to completely reverse large-scale deformations and elongate itself without increased force23. During this state, cells develop liquid-like properties and no longer become resistant to tension. In this study, mammalian epithelial cells were chosen because of their known ability to resist tension as well as their ability to pump water from their upper side to their lower side2. The water would then form a dome under the cells which would create tension and cause the cells to elongate (Figure 1a). During this process, some of the cells became superelastic, stretching to a wider cell surface than the elastic cells (Figure 1b). Adhesion junctions, the connecting area between cells, are the weakest points of pressure and eventually rupture from the increasing force. As a result, the water is able to escape from the dome which releases the tension from the cells (Figure 1c). Since none of the cells were in a state of plasticity, where irreversible damage can be done to the cellular shape3, all the cells return to their original, compacted position with superelastic cells appearing the same as other cells (Figure 1d). Previously, scientists believed cells under identical tension would have the same degree of shape deformation, but this experiment also shows that different cells have different thresholds for superelasticity. As shown in Figure 1, not all of the epithelial cells become superelastic at the same time, which researchers theorized was a result of the varied cellular mechanical properties (such as sensitivity to tension) of each cell2. Additionally, only under specific conditions can a cell enter a state of superelasticity. Cells that are placed under rapidly increasing pressure, even for a short duration, usually rupture while cells with slowly increasing pressure are able to maintain the dome structure for over hours2. Although this study has provided insight into a topic on which there was very limited understanding, there are still many questions left regarding cellular superelasticity. For one, there is still no definite reason as to why this occurs. Latorre et al. examined the connection between a cell’s cortex thickness and its superelastic threshold but there wasn’t substantial evidence supporting this hypothesis. The cell cortex is composed mainly of actin filaments, cytoskeletal filaments that maintain cellular structure and shape by relaying forces both within and between cells4. They hoped to show that cellular stretching resulted in the breaking apart of these filaments which would lead to a superelastic state, but the results didn’t show a direct correlation2. But, they were able to show the involvement of intermediate filaments, filaments that only provide mechanical strength to cells and are not involved in cellular movement1. When intermediate filaments in superelastic cells underwent laser ablation (essentially removing them), cell surface increased, which showed that they had resisted tension and were load-bearing (a theory that was suggested due to their unusually stiff structure in super-stretched cells)1. From this, they theorized that the weakness of the cortex induces support from the intermediate filaments and helps the cell elongate. Latorre, E., Kale, S., Casares, L., Gómez-González, M., Uroz, M., Valon, L., . . . Trepat, X. (2018, 10). Active superelasticity in three-dimensional epithelia of controlled shape. Nature, 563(7730), 203-208. doi:10.1038/s41586-018-0671-4 &amp;#8617; &amp;#8617;2 Théry, M., &amp;amp; Asnacios, A. (2018, 10). Cellular stretch reveals superelastic powers. Nature, 563(7730), 192-194. doi:10.1038/d41586-018-07172-9 &amp;#8617; &amp;#8617;2 &amp;#8617;3 &amp;#8617;4 &amp;#8617;5 Yirka, B. (2018, 11). Researchers find that cells can at times have superelastic properties. Retrieved from Phys.org website: https://phys.org/news/2018-11-cells-superelastic-properties.html &amp;#8617; Cooper GM. The Cell: A Molecular Approach. 2nd edition. Sunderland (MA): Sinauer Associates; 2000. Intermediate Filaments. Available from: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK9834/ &amp;#8617;</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/superelastic-cell-graphic.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Stanford Researchers Identify Human Bone Stem Cells</title><link href="/stanford-stem-cell/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stanford Researchers Identify Human Bone Stem Cells" /><published>2018-11-30T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-11-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/stanford-stem-cell</id><content type="html" xml:base="/stanford-stem-cell/">&lt;p&gt;In a study published on September 20, 2018, a team of researchers at the Stanford University of Medicine identified a multipotent human skeletal stem cell that gives rise to new bone or cartilage in the body. The implications of this study can lead to new regenerative treatments for fractures, arthritis, and bone injuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stem cells are cells that have not yet been differentiated and can self-renew for extremely long periods of time to keep their colonies intact. Once differentiated,  stem cells become specialized cells required for regenerative therapy. These cells then differentiate into specialized cells called progenitor cells, which make up human tissues. The adult stem cell is lineage-restricted, meaning that it can give rise only to certain types of tissue like bone, cartilage, and stroma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cell can also be isolated from human bone and even be generated from specialized cells in fat. They can also arise from induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs), a hot-topic technology in current stem cell research. The stem cell is found in increased quantities at the end of a developing bone or the site of a healing fracture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stem cells are different from mesenchymal stem cells, which have had limited success in various clinical trials. Mesenchymal stem cells are isolated from the blood, bone marrow, and fat, and are considered to be all-purpose stem cells. However, these stem cells are very loosely characterized and may actually comprise of a large variety of cell populations, which may account for why they respond differently and unpredictably to differentiation signals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In contrast, the skeletal stem cell we’ve identified possesses all of the hallmark qualities of true, multipotential, self-renewing, tissue-specific stem cells. They are restricted in terms of their fate potential to just skeletal tissues, which is likely to make them much more clinically useful,” said Charles K.F. Chan, PhD, assistant professor of surgery at Stanford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study is a large advancement for stem cell research partly because it does not include ethical complications that are otherwise attached to the field of stem cell research. Pluripotent stem cells are usually derived from embryonic stem cells, which come from human embryos and exist only at early developmental stages. This stem cell, in contrast, bides its time in adult tissue until it differentiates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There are 75 million Americans with arthritis, for example. Imagine if we could turn readily available fat cells from liposuction into stem cells that could be injected into their joints to make new cartilage, or if we could stimulate the formation of new bone to repair fractures in older people,” said Michael Longaker, MD, professor of plastic and reconstructive surgery at Stanford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another implication of the study is that it provides a technological advantage convenient for researchers working with human hematopoietic stem cells–that is, the stem cells in human bone marrow that give rise to the blood and immune system. These skeletal stem cells don’t require growth factors in the serum used as the environment containing hematopoietic stem cells. Instead, they provide an environment where hematopoietic stem cells can thrive. The stromal population that arises from the skeletal cell can keep hematopoietic stem cells alive for two weeks without the need for additional serum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers of the study also constructed a family tree of stem cells, which could be used in clinical applications and provide a way to understand the similarities and differences between mouse and human skeletal stem cells. This, in turn, may lead to discovery of key evolutionary differences between humans and mice. The researchers had used the mouse skeletal stem cell to locate and isolate the human skeletal stem cell by comparing gene expression profiles of the mouse skeletal stem cell with those of cell populations at the end of bones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would hope that, within the next decade or so, this cell source will be a game-changer in the field of arthroscopic and regenerative medicine,” Longaker noted. “If we can use this stem cell for relatively noninvasive therapies, it could be a dream come true.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>anjali_mangla_20</name></author><summary type="html">In a study published on September 20, 2018, a team of researchers at the Stanford University of Medicine identified a multipotent human skeletal stem cell that gives rise to new bone or cartilage in the body. The implications of this study can lead to new regenerative treatments for fractures, arthritis, and bone injuries.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/stem-cell-image.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ferrofluids: The Magnetic Liquid Dancer</title><link href="/ferrofluids/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ferrofluids: The Magnetic Liquid Dancer" /><published>2018-10-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-10-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/ferrofluids</id><content type="html" xml:base="/ferrofluids/">&lt;p&gt;The 1900s brought about countless exciting inventions from all across the globe. Sometimes a little mysterious, many of these inventions were intriguing and versatile. One such invention was the ferrofluid, a substance that serves a variety of purposes in fields ranging from rocket science to school science fairs.
Ferrofluids are commonly recognized as spiky liquids that “dance” under the influence of magnetic fields. Technically defined, ferrofluids are stable colloidal suspensions of superparamagnetic iron oxide nanoparticles. The magnetic property of ferrofluids derives from these tiny iron oxide particles. Because of these nanoparticles, ferrofluids do not stay magnetized after being removed from the presence of a magnetic field.
Patented in 1965 by NASA chemist Steven Papell at the Lewis Research Center, ferrofluids were initially developed by scientists intending to facilitate the transfer of rocket fuel into a spacecraft’s engine. In space, the lack of gravity allows fuel to float within the holding tank and makes it difficult for the fuel to be efficiently pumped into the engine. Papell envisioned transforming the non-magnetic fuel into one that could be controlled and guided by the maneuvering of magnetic fields.
Although Steven Papell’s idea was never practiced (as NASA preferred the use of solid rocket fuel to the concept of liquid magnetic fuel), it did incite the fervor to research this new magnetic substance. In fact, there was so much excitement surrounding ferrofluids that the mechanics of magnetic fluids was recognized as a new branch of science known as Ferrohydrodynamics.
Even after the rapid development of solid rocket propulsion technology eliminated the need for magnetic fuel, ferrofluids did not leave the realm of rocket science. Only a few years after their invention, ferrofluids were reconsidered for use in rockets, but this time to manage the spacecraft’s temperature: the temperature of the side of the rocket facing the sun is significantly higher than that of the side in shadow, which can introduce problems to the spacecraft.
	More recently, it was also found that ferrofluids could improve speakers. In loudspeakers, electric energy is sent through a coil near the center of a circular permanent magnet. The current running through the coil induces a magnetic field, causing the coil to vibrate and produce an amplified sound. By coating the coil in a ferrofluid, engineers are able to dampen unwanted resonances and dispel excess heat from the coil. As a result, the speaker is able to have better sound quality.
	Nowadays, ferrofluids are being developed and tested for potential use in the biomedical field. Medical researchers are hopeful that with magnetic fields, medicine can be transferred quickly and easily through the human body. Ferrofluids are also being used in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) techniques as contrast agents.
	In this fast-paced new era when inventions and innovations are constantly springing up from every corner, ferrofluids are no exception. Engineers and scientists in every field are coming up with more enhanced and creative ways to employ ferrofluids within their work. One could also say that ferrofluids are practically spiking up with unbridled potential!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Brief History of Ferrofluid. (2014, December 23). Retrieved October 12, 2018, from https://www.czferro.com/blog/2014/10/27/history-of-ferrofluids&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A. (2015, October 30). The Science Behind Ferrofluids. Retrieved October 12, 2018, from https://www.apexmagnets.com/news-how-tos/the-science-behind-ferrofluids/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferrofluid. (2008). Retrieved October 13, 2018, from https://archive.education.mrsec.wisc.edu/background/ferrofluid/index.html&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lockney, D. (n.d.). Magnetic Fluids Deliver Better Speaker Sound Quality. Retrieved October 13, 2018, from https://spinoff.nasa.gov/Spinoff2015/cg_2.html&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>claire_yuan_22</name></author><summary type="html">The 1900s brought about countless exciting inventions from all across the globe. Sometimes a little mysterious, many of these inventions were intriguing and versatile. One such invention was the ferrofluid, a substance that serves a variety of purposes in fields ranging from rocket science to school science fairs. Ferrofluids are commonly recognized as spiky liquids that “dance” under the influence of magnetic fields. Technically defined, ferrofluids are stable colloidal suspensions of superparamagnetic iron oxide nanoparticles. The magnetic property of ferrofluids derives from these tiny iron oxide particles. Because of these nanoparticles, ferrofluids do not stay magnetized after being removed from the presence of a magnetic field. Patented in 1965 by NASA chemist Steven Papell at the Lewis Research Center, ferrofluids were initially developed by scientists intending to facilitate the transfer of rocket fuel into a spacecraft’s engine. In space, the lack of gravity allows fuel to float within the holding tank and makes it difficult for the fuel to be efficiently pumped into the engine. Papell envisioned transforming the non-magnetic fuel into one that could be controlled and guided by the maneuvering of magnetic fields. Although Steven Papell’s idea was never practiced (as NASA preferred the use of solid rocket fuel to the concept of liquid magnetic fuel), it did incite the fervor to research this new magnetic substance. In fact, there was so much excitement surrounding ferrofluids that the mechanics of magnetic fluids was recognized as a new branch of science known as Ferrohydrodynamics. Even after the rapid development of solid rocket propulsion technology eliminated the need for magnetic fuel, ferrofluids did not leave the realm of rocket science. Only a few years after their invention, ferrofluids were reconsidered for use in rockets, but this time to manage the spacecraft’s temperature: the temperature of the side of the rocket facing the sun is significantly higher than that of the side in shadow, which can introduce problems to the spacecraft. More recently, it was also found that ferrofluids could improve speakers. In loudspeakers, electric energy is sent through a coil near the center of a circular permanent magnet. The current running through the coil induces a magnetic field, causing the coil to vibrate and produce an amplified sound. By coating the coil in a ferrofluid, engineers are able to dampen unwanted resonances and dispel excess heat from the coil. As a result, the speaker is able to have better sound quality. Nowadays, ferrofluids are being developed and tested for potential use in the biomedical field. Medical researchers are hopeful that with magnetic fields, medicine can be transferred quickly and easily through the human body. Ferrofluids are also being used in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) techniques as contrast agents. In this fast-paced new era when inventions and innovations are constantly springing up from every corner, ferrofluids are no exception. Engineers and scientists in every field are coming up with more enhanced and creative ways to employ ferrofluids within their work. One could also say that ferrofluids are practically spiking up with unbridled potential!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/ferrofluid.jpg" /></entry></feed>